Aleksandra Nenadic, PhD

Training Lead, Software Sustainability Institute

Location: Office 1.17 Kilburn Building, Oxford Road M13 9PL Telephone: +44 (0)161 275 0672

Email: a.nenadic@manchester.ac.uk

ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2269-3894

Professional profile

Over the past 5 years committed to ongoing improvement of research software practice through training and community engagement work in UK's Software Sustainability Institute and ELIXIR EU Life Sciences Infrastructure Project. Driving the training trends forward by helping communities roll out new training strategies and curricula for research in individual domains. Maintained UK's pivotal role within the international Carpentries community delivering Software, Data, Library and HPC Carpentry training, drove key strategic decisions and handled international collaborations and outreach with training communities.

Career summary

June 2016 - present

Software Sustainability Institute, UK

Training Team Lead

- Working to improve the provision and access to training in foundational computational and data management skills and best practices for open and reproducible research for UK researchers across domains by diffusion of a model of training based on pedagogical research and principles of openness, inclusivity, accessibility and collaboration. To date, this work helped train ~6000 researchers at ~200 workshops and build a thriving, diverse and inclusive community of ~200 instructors, mentors and training material developers around the UK alone.
- Engaging with UK HE institutions, universities, CDTs and projects involving training by providing consultancy, guidance and support, and with the UK Research Software Engineering Society and various communities of practice formed around research software on collaboratively building a computationally-skilled researcher base.

2014 - 2016

ELIXIR EU Life Sciences Infrastructure Project

Technical Training Coordinator and Senior System Architect

- Helped roll out Software and Carpentry programmes in EU and UK by training ~280 life sciences researchers and 20 instructors from 13 EU countries and facilitated further growth of the Carpentry communities in Europe in various other domains.
- Designed, co-developed and project managed the implementation of TeSS training portal for browsing and automated discovery of life sciences training resources aggregated from ELIXIR nodes and 3rd-party providers.

2002 - 2014 University of Manchester, UK

Product manager (2013 - 2014)
Senior Research Software Engineer (2010 - 2013)
Research Software Engineer (2008 - 2010)
Post Doctoral Researcher (2006 - 2008)
Research Associate (2002 - 2006)

- Product manager for <u>Taverna</u> and <u>BioCatalogue</u> projects.
- Developing Web registries, services, portal applications and scientific workflow execution software (<u>Taverna</u>, <u>BioCatalogue</u>, <u>BioVel</u>, <u>SCAPE EU</u>, <u>NelSS</u> projects).
- Research and development of a number of security-related projects:
 Shibboleth-enabled Bridge to Access the National Grid Service (FAME-PERMIS),
 feasibility study for JISC including requirements engineering and consulting on levels of authentication assurance for the UK Research and Higher Education communities (eS-LoA), Single Sign-On solution for multi-level user authentication and federated identity and access management (FAME), prototype for secure online exchange of digital goods (FIDES).

2000 - 2001 eMobile (UK) Ltd., Manchester, UK

Software engineer

1999 - 2000 DUEL, Belgrade, Serbia

ORACLE database developer

Activities

- Curriculum Advisory Committee Member Public Health and Health Data Research -2018-2019
- Conference Organiser CarpentryCon Madison, US 2019-2020
- Conference Organiser/Project Manager CarpentryConnect Manchester 2019
- **Health Data Research Training Panel** HDR UK Health data science fellows network 2018
- Instructed at 25 Carpentry Workshops and hosted 12 Carpentry Workshops -2014-2019
- Volunteer and workshop helper EuroPython Edinburgh 2018
- Co-lead of the BioSchema community for the development of BioSchemas for life sciences training materials - a standard Schema.org markup to structure online training resources in life sciences - 2015-2016
- Carpentries workshop organiser & instructor 21 events 2015-present

Education and qualifications

- ILM Level 5 Award in Leadership & Management with Project Management -Institute of Leadership and Management - 2019
- Carpentries Instructor Trainer 2017
- Certified Data Carpentry Instructor Data Carpentry 2016
- Certified Software Carpentry Instructor Software Carpentry 2014
- PhD in Computer Science University of Manchester, UK 2005
- BSc in Mathematics and Computer Science (1st class Hons) University of Belgrade,
 Serbia 1999

Selected recent publications

Refereed

Larcombe, L., Hendricusdottir, R., Attwood, T. et al. (2017). ELIXIR-UK role in bioinformatics training at the national level and across ELIXIR. F1000Research 2017, 6:952 https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.11837.1

Pawlik, A., van Gelder, C., Nenadic, A. et al. (2017) Developing a strategy for computational lab skills training through Software and Data Carpentry: Experiences from the ELIXIR Pilot action F1000Research, 6:1040, https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.11718.1

Nenadic, A., Beard, N., Thurston, M., Sansone, S. A., Goble, C. A., & Attwood, T. (2016). TeSS–Training Portal. F1000Research, 5.

Ison, J. et al. (2016). Tools and data services registry: a community effort to document bioinformatics resources. (2016). Nucleic Acids Res., 44(D1):D38-47. doi: 10.1093/nar/gkv1116

Beard, N., Nenadic, A., Attwood, T., Goble, C., Thurston, M., & Sansone, S. A. (2015). ELIXIR's Training eSupport System—TeSS. F1000Research, 4.

Unrefereed

Nenadic, A., Sufi, S. (2019), CarpentryConnect Manchester 2019 Conference (CCMcr19) (2019). Report, https://zenodo.org/record/3458023.

Sufi, S., Aragon, S., Nenadic, A., Software Sustainability Institute's Event Organisation Guide (2019). https://event-organisation-guide.readthedocs.io/en/latest/.